<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Writing on Lalit Maganti</title><link>https://lalitm.com/tags/writing/</link><description>Recent content in Writing on Lalit Maganti</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 20:14:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lalitm.com/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>When Good Technical Writing Isn't Enough</title><link>https://lalitm.com/on-why-i-write-this-blog/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 20:14:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lalitm.com/on-why-i-write-this-blog/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, I came across &lt;a href="https://www.humaninvariant.com/blog/audience"&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t Build an Audience&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a fascinating post and has been occupying a lot of my &amp;ldquo;free thinking&amp;rdquo; time. I strongly suggest reading it as it&amp;rsquo;s well written and excellently argued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarise what it tries to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The market for written content on the web (blog posts, articles etc) is &amp;ldquo;efficient&amp;rdquo;: in other words, great work will find its audience without you needing to build a &amp;ldquo;following&amp;rdquo; first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Liquidity providers&amp;rdquo; (influencers, curators, algorithms) are incentivized to share good content because it benefits them. They maintain credibility and engagement by surfacing quality work. Specifically called out are Substack, Alexey Guzey and Tyler Cowen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can speed up &amp;ldquo;distribution&amp;rdquo; of what you write with minimal effort. Just 30 minutes to email a few key people and posts on the &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; platforms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, focus on creating excellent work rather than &amp;ldquo;building an audience&amp;rdquo;. If it&amp;rsquo;s truly good, the market will ensure it reaches &amp;ldquo;everyone who matters&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a very strong believer in the core message of &amp;ldquo;make cool things rather than chase followers&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve done throughout my life and I have zero interest in changing that going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don&amp;rsquo;t agree with the argument that that market is efficient for &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; types of written content. I think the author is over-indexing on what they write about: topics accessible for a wide audience and do not require background knowledge (e.g. philosophical musings, economic theory, social dynamics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I write about deeply &lt;a href="https://lalitm.com/cast-x-as-string-casts-to-integer-in-sqlite/"&gt;technical&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://lalitm.com/perfetto-swiss-army-knife/"&gt;topics&lt;/a&gt;. Sometimes this can be so &lt;a href="https://lalitm.com/til-will-change-and-isolation-css-properties/"&gt;in the weeds&lt;/a&gt; that maybe at most a thousand people in the world will care about it. But it &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; totally change how these people work: maybe it tells them something important that they didn&amp;rsquo;t know about, adds a new technique or tool to their toolkit or even inspires them build something entirely new.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>