<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Til on Lalit Maganti</title><link>https://lalitm.com/tags/til/</link><description>Recent content in Til on Lalit Maganti</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 23:44:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lalitm.com/tags/til/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>TIL: Diátaxis: Systematic technical documentation</title><link>https://lalitm.com/til-diataxis-systematic-technical-documentation/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 23:44:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lalitm.com/til-diataxis-systematic-technical-documentation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I &lt;a href="https://lalitm.com/til-the-documentation-system-divio/"&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; about &amp;ldquo;The Documentation System&amp;rdquo; and how valuable I found it. As I dug deeper into researching how best to apply the principles outlined there, I came across &lt;a href="https://diataxis.fr/"&gt;Diátaxis&lt;/a&gt;. Written by the same author after they left &lt;a href="https://www.divio.com/"&gt;Divio&lt;/a&gt;, Diátaxis is a distillation of all the principles with much more guidance in how to apply the framework (e.g. giving more examples), diving more into the philosophy and in general being a more comprehensive view into how to write great technical docs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m blown away by how well the framework (and Diátaxis &lt;a href="https://diataxis.fr/how-to-use-diataxis/#use-diataxis-as-a-guide-not-a-plan"&gt;makes clear&lt;/a&gt; it is a framework &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; a rigid set of rules) is explained. It&amp;rsquo;s patently obvious that the author really understands technical documentation and they truly have given a gift to the industry by writing it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding Diátaxis has only made me more motivated to deeply absorb its principles and see how to best apply it to all technical documentation I refactor and/or write going forward.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>TIL: Public File Hosting with 0x0.st</title><link>https://lalitm.com/til-public-file-hosting-with-0x0-st/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 15:13:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://lalitm.com/til-public-file-hosting-with-0x0-st/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you run into a truly inspirational piece of software that it&amp;rsquo;s a wonder even exists. I found &lt;a href="https://0x0.st/"&gt;0x0.st&lt;/a&gt; recently and it very much falls into this bucket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s essentially a simple, no-account, temporary file hosting site where you can just upload a file using a simple HTTP POST and the site will host it for you for between 30 days and 1 year depending on the size of the file. Uploading a file is as simple as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex="0"&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl -F &amp;#39;file=@yourfile.ext&amp;#39; https://0x0.st
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;and you&amp;rsquo;ll get back a URL that you can share or use in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought all the services like this had long since disappeared especially in the age of increasing scrutiny by government of content that websites host. It turns out though that from this discussion on &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=35491520"&gt;HN&lt;/a&gt;, there are actually a bunch of similar services (transfer.sh, bashupload.com, chunk.io) but 0x0.st was the only one which I was able to access without an error.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>TIL: `will-change` and `isolation` CSS properties</title><link>https://lalitm.com/til-will-change-and-isolation-css-properties/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:20:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://lalitm.com/til-will-change-and-isolation-css-properties/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Perfetto UI is a fascinating project to work on because it often faces performance problems which you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t see in more &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; webapps. I learn about all sorts of weird web features by reviewing PRs for the UI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two such features I just learned about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/will-change"&gt;will-change&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="https://github.com/google/perfetto/pull/3350/files#diff-c57fa71e0c282ce81f65b10226043f6d89c4105afd3f5ec5813b8d9d5e034101R128"&gt;PR&lt;/a&gt;): a hint, to be used sparingly, to tell the browser that a certain property of a DOM element will change in the near future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/isolation"&gt;isolation&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/google/perfetto/pull/3381/files#diff-c57fa71e0c282ce81f65b10226043f6d89c4105afd3f5ec5813b8d9d5e034101R119"&gt;PR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;):
I feel MDN didn&amp;rsquo;t do a great job of explaining so I asked Claude which gave a much more useful answer:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;isolation is a CSS property that creates a new stacking context for an element. Think of a stacking context as a self-contained z-index universe. Elements within one stacking context can layer on top of each other, but their z-index values only matter relative to siblings within that same context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>TIL: The Documentation System (Divio)</title><link>https://lalitm.com/til-the-documentation-system-divio/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2025 19:38:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://lalitm.com/til-the-documentation-system-divio/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Perfetto team spent a lot of time earlier this year rewriting our documentation to be more useful for the average developer. We struggled a lot to figure out &amp;ldquo;what is the best way to structure our documentation&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When reading &lt;a href="https://rakhim.exotext.com/examples-are-the-best-documentation"&gt;Examples are the best documentation&lt;/a&gt; today, I came across &lt;a href="https://docs.divio.com/documentation-system/"&gt;The Documentation System&lt;/a&gt;, an approach to structuring developer documentation. Reading through it, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but marvel at how clear and concisely it laid out the ideas we were struggling to come up with from first principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, I really like how it breaks down documentation into four quadrants:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.divio.com/documentation-system/tutorials/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tutorials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: take your user through a series of steps to complete some task with your project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.divio.com/documentation-system/how-to-guides/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How-to guides&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: solve a real world problem with your project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.divio.com/documentation-system/reference/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference guides&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: give technical explanations of how things work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.divio.com/documentation-system/explanation/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: clarify a particular topic or area and how the project fits into the bigger tech landscape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we got &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; of this right in our documentation rewrite but we definitely muddled some of these areas together, making our pages less clear than they could be. I plan on spending some time later this year correcting our docs to match this system closer.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>